Ana Luísa Pinho

BrainsCAN Postdoctoral Fellow

Western Interdisciplinary Research Building, room 4130 Western University, Dock 76 1151 Richmond St N London, Ontario N6A 3K7, Canada

https://alpinho.github.io/

agrilopi@uwo.ca

Google Scholar: ana.luisa.pinho

ORCID: 0000-0001-8718-0902

About Me –

I am a Neuroscientist with a background in Engineering Physics. My research focuses on the application of functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI), computational and statistical techniques —including machine learning— to map neurocognitive mechanisms in the human brain.

Expertise

Plan&Organize Multistep Projects

Analysis of High-Dimensional Data

Scientific Writing

Languages

Portuguese

English

French



Social Network -



@alpinho

@ALuisaPinho@fediscience.org

@ALuisaPinho

linkedin.com/in/analuisapinho

Memberships



Member of the Organization for Human Brain Mapping



Member of the Portuguese Society for Neuroscience

Professional Experience

2021 - Present Tier I BrainsCAN Postdoctoral Fellow

Western University, CA

- Functional mapping of the cortico-striatal-cerebellar circuitry involved in the cognitive ability of forming temporal predictions during rhythmic and non-rhythmic sequences of events.
- · Development of individualized encoding models (that better account for inter-subject variability) to improve functional specificity in neuroimaging of the cognitive mapping of elementary components associated with human behaviour.

2015 - 2020 **Postdoctoral Researcher**

Parietal Team - Inria Saclay, FR

- Development of the Individual Brain Charting (IBC) dataset, an open-access, multi-task fMRI-data initiative.
- · Development of an individual-functional-atlasing approach to link functional segregation of specialized brain regions to elementary mental functions, by leveraging the IBC dataset.

Education

Postgraduate

2009 - 2015 PhD

Karolinska Institutet, SE and University of Coimbra, PT

Biomedical Sciences

Thesis: Inside of the Creative Mind: Unravelling the Neurocognitive Mechanisms of Musical Creativity

Undergraduate

1999 - 2008

MSc + Licentiate Degrees

Instituto Superior Técnico - ULisboa, PT

Foundation for Science and Technology, PT

Engineering Physics

Thesis: Probabilistic non-linear earthquake location in a 3-D velocity model

Fellowships, Grants & Awards

2021 - Present BrainsCAN Postdoc. Fellowship

Canada First Research Excellence Fund, CA

Amount (3y): 225K CAD

2013 - 2014**Research Fellowship** Sven and Dagmar Saléns Foundation, SE

Amount: \sim **144K SEK**

2013 Prize of The Best Poster Communication Rectory of NOVA ULisboa, PT

> Symposium "Music, Poetry & The Brain -Celebrating Wagner's Bicentennial"

2009 - 2013PhD Studentship

SFRH/BD/33895/2009 Amount: ~**80K** €

2006 - 2007 **Scientific Initiation Grant** Foundation for Science and Technology, PT

Seismology

Amount: ~3.600 €

Ad Hoc Reviewer

Journals

Cerebral Cortex, NeuroImage, Scientific Data, Scientific Reports, Brain Structure and Function, Brain Imaging and Behavior, Frontiers in Psychology and PeerJ Computer Science

Ana Luísa Pinho

BrainsCAN Postdoctoral Fellow

Computer Skills —

Programming

Python (venv, pytest, Joblib), Bash, C, SQL, Lisp, Assembly (Harvard Arquitecture)

Scientific Computing

IPython, NumPy, SciPy, pingouin, MATLAB, GNU Octave, Jupyter Notebook, R, Wolfram Mathematica

Machine-Learning Frameworks

scikit-learn, Google AI&ML Transformers

pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn

A Typesetting

LETEX (Document Classes: article, beamer, book and letter)

Software for Neuroimaging

Nilearn, NiBabel, SPM, FSL, FreeSurfer, Papaya, Connectome Workbench, MRIcron, MRIcroGL, BrainVoyager

Software for Psychophysics

Expyriment, pliers, Psychtoolbox, E-Prime&E-Basic, PsychoPy, Presentation

Software Engineering

Git protocol (Platforms: GitHub and GitLab), Conda

■ Web/Databases

HTML&CSS, Django

Miscellaneous

GNU Emacs, gnuplot, Visual Studio Code, Office productivity softwares, GIMP, Inkscape, darktable, Unison File Synchronizer, VeraCrypt, FFmpeg, Kdenlive, Statistica (by StatSoft and TIBCO Software)

Selected Publications

2023 Individual Brain Charting third release, probing brain activity

during Movie Watching and Retinotopic Mapping

<u>Ana Luísa Pinho</u> et al. preprint in HAL. Journal article submitted.

2023 Should one go for individual or group-level brain parcellations?

A deep-phenotyping benchmark.

Bertrand Thirion, Himanshu Aggarwal, Ana Fernanda

Ponce, <u>Ana Luísa Pinho</u>, and Alexis Thual Brain Struct Funct. Online ahead of print.

From deep brain phenotyping to functional atlasing.

Bertrand Thirion, Alexis Thual, and Ana Luísa Pinho

Curr Opin Behav Sci. 40:201-202

2021 Subject-specific segregation of functional territories based on

deep phenotyping <u>Ana Luísa Pinho</u> et al.

Hum Brain Mapp. 42(4):841-870

2020 Individual Brain Charting dataset extension, second release of

high-resolution fMRI data for cognitive mapping.

<u>Ana Luísa Pinho</u> et al. Sci Data. 7(1):353

2018 Individual Brain Charting, a high-resolution fMRI dataset for cog-

nitive mapping <u>Ana Luísa Pinho</u> et al. Sci Data. 5:180105

Selected Dataset Publications

2021 Individual Brain Charting (IBC)

<u>Ana Luísa Pinho</u> et al. EBRAINS. v3.0

2020 Individual Brain Charting dataset extension, second release of

high-resolution fMRI data for cognitive mapping

Ana Luísa Pinho et al.

NeuroVault, id collection=6618

Selected Software Contributions

2021 – Present Contributer to **WiNRepo**: "Women in Neuroscience Repository" 2017 – Present Contributer to **Nilearn**: Stats&ML for NeuroImaging in Python 2015 – Present Contributer to **Public Analysis Code for the IBC Project**

2015 – 2020 Contributer to **Public Protocols for the IBC Project**

Selected Talks

2023 Deep behavioral phenotyping in functional MRI for cognitive

mapping of the human brain

Seminar at the MNI Feindel Brain and Mind Lecture Series, BIC and

MNI, McGill University, Montreal, Canada

2020 Segregation of functional territories in individual brains

Oral presentation in Session Modeling and Analysis: Variability in

Brain Activation, OHBM Annual (Virtual) Meeting

2020 Individual Brain Charting dataset extension: second and third

releases

Open Science Room, OHBM Annual (Virtual) Meeting

2019 Individual Brain Charting, a high-resolution fMRI dataset for

cognitive mapping of the human brain The 5th CiNet Conference, Osaka, Japan

Advocacy

Gender Equity Board member of the Women in Neuroscience Repository (WiNRepo)

January 2, 2024

Ana Luísa Pinho